Finding Aid for Michael D. Whitty Papers 1986-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michael D. Whitty papers 1986-1995
Whitty, Michael D., 1942-
Professor of management and labor relations at the University of Detroit-Mercy; researcher and lecturer on social issues within the business world. Studies include the impact of AIDS within the workplace. Biographical information, publications and conference papers, collected material relating to AIDS and AIDS awareness.
0163 Aa 2
0.8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were given to Cruise Magazine from an unknown donor. The magazine later gave the materials to Midwest AIDS Prevention Project. The library received the materials in August 2001. Donor no. 9122.
The collection is open for research.
Michael D. Whitty (1942-) researches and lectures locally and abroad regarding social issues within the business world. His studies include AIDS in the workplace, the Americans with Disabilities Act, the global workplace, men's health, the role of spirituality within the business world and the future of work. Whitty, also known as Dr. Detroit, is an activist involved with workers' rights, sensitivity in business, and various AIDS organizations. Some of his activities include the Global Health Promotion Project, the AIDS Law Project, Corporate AIDS Project, and the AIDS Education Project. His education includes an A.B. from the University of Detroit (1960), an M.A. from the University of Michigan (1964), and a PhD from Syracuse University (1969). He is currently a professor of Management and Labor Relations at the University of Detroit-Mercy.
The Michael D. Whitty papers detail his professional and personal interest in AIDS during the late 1980s and early 1990s. The majority of the collection consists of research papers regarding AIDS policy in Michigan workplaces. Whitty presented his findings at several conferences focusing on AIDS in business. His personal interest in AIDS and human rights is best documented in his topical files.
Subjects:
Whitty, Michael D., 1942-; AIDS (Disease)--Economic aspects.
- Biographical
  The biographical series consists of one folder. It contains vitae, bibliographies, and several short biographical sketches of Whitty.
  - Miscellaneous biographical materials (Box 1)
- Papers and Publications
  The papers and publications series is divided into articles written or co-authored by Michael Whitty and collected papers by other authors. The majority are non-published works by Whitty and his colleagues. Many of the papers address AIDS issues within the business world including employee relations, curriculum development, sensitivity training, health accessibility, and legal issues.
  - Authored by Michael Whitty
    - ADA/HIV undated (Box 1)
    - AIDS: Looking into the 1990s undated (Box 1)
    - AIDS & International Management undated (Box 1)
      written with Matthew Seeger and Michele Simms
    - AIDS in Business 1989 (Box 1)
      alternate title: Teaching About AIDS in Education and Business
    - AIDS in the Workplace: A Matter for Urgent Corporate Action 1991 (Box 1)
    - AIDS in the Workplace: Does It Belong in the Business School Curriculum? undated (Box 1)
      written with Bonnie Fremgen and Michele Simms
    - AIDS, Labor Law, and Good Management 1989 (Box 1)
    - Bisexuality and AIDS: A North American Report 1991 (Box 1)
    - Corporate AIDS Policy Response in One Midwestern City 1992 (Box 1)
      written with Bonnie Fremgen
    - Corporate Communication undated (Box 1)
    - Corporate Response to the ADA in One City 1994 (Box 1)
      written with Martin Adrukonis
    - Employers Ten Commandments for Dealing with AIDS in the Workplace undated (Box 1)
    - Global AIDS: The Necessity for Effective Communications Systems undated (Box 1)
    - Global AIDS: The Transnational Challenge undated (Box 1)
    - The Global Management Challenge of AIDS in the Workplace undated (Box 1)
    - How To Avoid a Costly AIDS Crisis in the Organization 1992 (Box 1)
    - Management Education for Policy Formation for AIDS and Other Life-Threatening Diseases undated (Box 1)
    - Overview of Labor: Bargaining Issues Concerning AIDS for Public Employers 1988 (Box 1)
    - Positive Management Counteracting Workplace Fear: Developing an AIDS Policy for Hospitals undated (Box 1)
      written with Walter B. Connolly, Jr.
    - Sex, Death, and Work: Management Education to Confront AIDS undated (Box 1)
    - [Student Views Regarding AIDS] undated (Box 1)
    - Teaching About AIDS in Education and Business undated (Box 1)
    - Teaching AIDS and Aids in Teaching undated (Box 1)
      written with Matt Seeger and Michelle Simms
    - What AIDS Education Offers to Business Management undated (Box 1)
    - Working Paper 90-6: AIDS, the Workplace and Health Promotion 1990 (Box 1)
  - Other Authors
    - AIDS in the Fire Service: A Practical Approach for Setting Fire Department Policy, by Dave L. Silvani 1990 (Box 1)
    - AIDS in the Fire Service II: A Practical Look Back: A Practical Look Forward, by Dave L. Silvani 1994 (Box 1)
    - AIDS in the Workplace, by Margaret M. Nagel 1989 (Box 1)
    - AIDS in the Workplace: A Review of the Issues, by Sondra Byrnes 1988 (Michigan Consolidated Gas Company) (Box 1)
    - Co-Management-Employees Co-Manage With Owner Beyond Employee Involvement, by John M. Buhager and Andrea Caulfield 1990 (Box 1)
    - Corporate Social Responses: A Predictive Model and Test Using the Policy Issue of AIDS in the Workplace, by Valerie E. Mock 1991 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Bar Association AIDS and Employment Law Seminar, by Mark Brewer 1990 (Box 1)
    - The Evolving Response to AIDS, by Noel Fletcher 1992 (Box 1)
    - Hospital Policy Management of Exposures to Blood-Borne Viral Diseases, by Walter B. Connolly, Jr. undated (Box 1)
    - Positive Management Counteracting Workplace Fear: Developing an AIDS Policy for Hospitals, by Henry Barraco, Patricia Bentley, Marlene Bryk, Bassam Chaballout, George Collier, Annette Cords, Alicia Green, and Beth Merrill 1988 (Box 1)
- Conferences
  The next series details conferences Whitty attended and, in most cases, at which he presented papers. Each folder contains conference itineraries and accompanying material. Some of the folders contain correspondence concerning the lectures, presentation transcripts, planning meeting minutes, event publicity, and clippings. One folder, AIDS in the Workplace, includes a survey research project. It samples opinions regarding AIDS policy and employee relations across Michigan businesses. The questionnaire and survey data are included in the folder.
  - 1987 Health & Politics: In an Age of AIDS (Birmingham, Michigan) (Box 1)
  - 1990
    - AIDS in the Court: Infection Control Policy and Procedure Development Seminar (Michigan Judicial Institute, Ann Arbor, Michigan) (Box 1)
    - International Congress on AIDS: AIDS, a New Global Challenge: Impacts on Developing Countries (Chulabhorn Research Institute, Bangkok, Thailand) (Box 1)
  - 1991 AIDS in the Workplace (Box 1)
    includes survey materials; Detroit, Michigan
  - 1992 Business Response to AIDS (national teleconference) (Box 1)
  - 1994 Michigan Responds to AIDS in the Workplace (University of Detroit-Mercy, Detroit, Michigan) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous conferences (Box 1)
  - Speech notes (Box 1)
- Topical Files Regarding AIDS
  The topical files series include AIDS-related materials collected by Whitty. Included are policies of Michigan companies and public organizations. His role as an activist is shown through his files regarding AIDS support and awareness groups.
  - Hate Crimes (Box 1)
  - Legal Issues (Box 1)
  - Michigan Department of Public Health (Box 1)
  - Michigan State Board of Education (Box 1)
  - Organizations
    - Campaign to End Homophobia (Box 1)
    - Detroit Chapter of the NAMES Project AIDS Memorial Quilt (Box 1)
    - Labor Groups (Box 1)
    - Michigan Campaign for Human Dignity (Box 1)
    - Trade Union Minorities/Women Leadership Training Project of Michigan (Box 1)
  - Policy and Procedure
    - City of Ann Arbor, Michigan (Box 1)
    - Commercial Businesses (Box 1)
    - Health Care Providers (Box 1)
  - Support Groups and Resources (Box 1)